Morning thank you house everybody doing...build.
Excellentthank you very much I.
what's new in csharp six what's new in visual basic fourteen we're talking about
this morning my name's dustin camel I work on the manage languages team
focusing on id experiences intelligence that sort of thing and my compiled
...my cohort mass jorgensen I'm the...language lead so I work
...work on csharp the language but I love vb that's right that's right so
actually we're going to focus pretty heavily on csharp today we're going to
...demos and...going to be in csharp code what I want but I do want to mention that things that we
...today are pretty much all in visual basic and,
we'll make noted that as we go throughout of over-trying we're going to stick and csharp keep things,
things kind of simple but, that is truth and you can take that to the...so?
Don't forget...submit eval's your what we do it now if you're feeling good if
you're sceptical wait till the end okay but don't do now that's okay we're
...just...here?
So, it's been a really big here.
...here last year imagine I...up here just last year and,
it was an exciting time for us does ...who remembers that last year we did some really cool things we
started talking about csharp six we had done a couple of talks here in there at
...very smaller conferences digits start, you know,
testing the waters and then we came here and really give a big reveal about what we're thinking about
what we're looking at talk about some experimental features and,
what might end up in the language at that time were thinking was we also last year were
released dot...compiler platform or project roslyn
...we really set on open-source on code...and, also shipped
...end-user preview and sdk previewing really was kind of us coming up for air we had
been laser focused on this thing for a number of years and finally coming up for
air and then this past year we
have been completely breathing oxygen free and clear in the world and, we have taken the time we...
associate language features we're going to talk about that today show you what's actually n perhaps maybe mention
a few guys that are...make the cut but,
really what the cohesive set of features that make-up csharp six and make it what it
is when I talk about today we're...we should mention that since
then we've also shipped like a number of times like eight times we
ships six public visual studio twenty fifteen...we...a previewing november we ship
and rc the other day so we've been shipping like crazy sense and that's been helping in
this refining process we released...dot net core libraries and runtime on as os on
get hub that was a big step as well...released in april ...released roslyn
and then in november of the...net core guys went up on get hub
kind of paving the way for us in january to move to get hub so
which has been very exciting so it's been a big year for us as well and finally we
open-source the remainder...code based on get...when we went out last year was just
a compilers just the api is on top of those compilers...now if we release the
entire stack the entire language stack of the ies really scripting api is
an interactive window and this current state of all those projects
...that kind of under the roslyn umbrella so it's been a really,
really big...yes huge?
Huge been a lot of fun so,
we can't just talk about some of that today we want to share what csharp
...look like when you get individual studio what is csharp six
what is visual basic fourteen going to feel like when you get in there so we want to talk about id features
...talk about analyzers encode fixes which is a huge topic of, you know,
coming some of the some of the really...z features coming out of...
work we didn't project roslyn to put static analysis and the id and, in your build system
can't talk about new language features of course we have to do that and that is most important thing
we're going to talk about some debugging features we've done by things
...the target is the title the talk yes ...
take a peek at what's next I walked around talk to a...beforehand and everybody was like...want to
...and csharp seven tells what csharp sevens like and,
you know, so, we'll talk a little bit about that though to be fair and have a lot of secrets these
days all that going on get a means that a lot of information is there and you can be involved
in discussion we'll talk about some of that as well all right so what...again?
...all right so.
This is visual studio two thousand fifteen rc this-is I'm going to talk about some of
these id features of this looks exactly like visual studio twenty thirteen is a
completely boring demo if you have if you have tried out visual studio twenty fifteen though,
you know, that's not true we this is completely rebuilt from scratch from visual
...twenty thirteen bringing in a brand-new...language service and editing experience for csharp
and visual basic so what you'll see here you see it looks very similar but as you work with the id
you're going to find things that are just a little bit different as we took
the time to rebuild some of these features and rethink them some of the features now...
a little bit better they've been refreshed so, for example, if I hover over variables you'll see things like,
you know, things look colorful now right there's look lipset appear it's
all very fancy little pieces a color it's even something so, mundane as, for example,
if I collapse and outlining region something has been the product sense the beginnings and visual studio net
twenty twenty two actually?
Outlining if I hover over that you see all of the rich semantic information of the syntax highlighting underneath
...of there so just taking the time to make things a little bit better.
Interestingly if I.
Up here though we've done some things be different and this is kind of experience of people start
seeing and immediately starting things like baited using directives where.
Basically we've taken something that comes from
...other modern id a feature that's very calmly calmly...across,
across other ideas we want to bring individual studio so the some of these using
director faded out because they are unnecessary now as you move around the id
you find things that are fated...starts telling you things small things warnings errors and,
in fated code there's a little libel that appears over here click on that light
It gives me actions I can do those actions come with
a really sweet preview.
That's a different...showing what will happen to your code if you were to do this
it's like we're taking a snapshot into the future
looking into the future and figure out what your code base is going to look like and giving you a picture of that very cool so
what's also cool about this though down here at the very bottom of this preview window
gives you a couple commands preview changes document project setting you can fix-all occurrences
in those scopes so...click on project for the first-time.
We can there we go we remove all use all the all of
unused using across the project right or across a solution so I can apply this if you look over
the solution explore z right now that there are no changes but they starting check marks
where changes occured and I can...and you see them go away and come back.
Go away combat school exciting.
As we as we go through the id union so start seeing some of these things pop up the...
appear sometimes you want to a transformation...refactoring or something you're...walking through you see something
...change and, it's not real obvious how to get the libel do appear
...as a keyboard shortcut...an important shortcut...might maybe the most important short-cut in
...control dot and that will always bring up a lightbulb and,
if I...expression say I want to do something with expression maybe...introduce a local variable for
...control dot they'll bring up...lightbulb with that great preview so
you can see that down here telling me what's going to.
Bring that up introduce a local.
And, I'm put into yet another new experience as part of visual
...fifteen...back through and we started re implementing some of
these features like rename the rename refactoring we realize we want didn't want to do
it at all like it was before if you remember renamed you press ftwo or control
...and...possible mobile dialogue...you type in a new name and then you can wait
while the dialogue comes up and makes the changes it's not really a fluids and...takes you out of your coding
...keep you right in the editor in the coding fluid like you're used to
doing so this local is given a given an initial name but you see the result
feeling to it down below...as I type.
It changes all across the editor so I can see whereby changes are occurring where that where
that was affected in the file and of course even if I were to
make a conflict so notice of the dashboard of...top...one unresolved conflict unresolved
conflict that's down here down the very bottom of the file see the routine down here there's
already a variable called routine so this would be a conflict that would that would break my program...let, you know,
about that right...ambient information as you're typing as you're using the features
keeping your program working so we're not going to actually stop you from doing this you could
very well trying to do this as a stepping stone to some
larger refactoring so this might be exactly what you want to do so it's okay to
applied here but I'm not going to I'm going to keep on typing.
Much into something else I'm going to change into the name
that's right below it there's and there's a field
call routines offset so come down here and this time is a conflict but
it's resolve...is something we...just fix for-you automatically see so, it already because there's a field
call routines offset inserts this dot for-you.
This is a piece of...of the id now that is also a extensible the idea of to encoder
...an extensible thing this...on top of roslyn and,
that idea of doing smart refactoring that fix conflicts for you there's a whole system built
around this dot is child's play doesn't crazy things to make sure that you program
stays correct with regard at least to the semantics...defined by the language so,
that's just one example we have a couple other...in here today that was a new
refactoring for the product introduce local people been asking for years of the opposite of
that is inline temporary variables operas control dot again and this one takes that expression is
assigned to the local and inserts it wherever the locals use removing...local after it's done and
you can see here the preview that's exactly what's going to do is...movies comput expression
memory dot read word right in there so go ahead and apply that.
Now this time the what's interesting is that this dot is
fated now because it's no longer necessary right because I know longer have a local that
conflicts with its name so it's fades that out for me in the editor and I
press control dot and there we go so that's just kind of a quick look at some of the new id
features what...you're going to have let's take a look.
At something though a little more meaningful from the perspective how we're going to
...we envision these this static analysis and code fixes and how we want
to expose this two guys and ecosystemas use libraries so I've got a
pretty simple application here extremely simple demo fodder I would say and,
what does it news up a couple of arrays...their length right so most of you should be able to
...what this does just by...the program...envision exactly what's going to
...represent five to prove it imprints the length of to arrays we create an empty...we
create an array of five elements and we printed them so?
...developer maybe that's interested in the dot net
immutable collection and I've used arrays before so I know-how those work I can new them up and I can check
...everything's good however.
So, I start using the immutable raisins...a picture.
...is it's ...part of the system dot collections...immutable new get package
...available it's open-source on get hub is part...core part of the
cortex project so kind of the equivalent code new...up an empty array would be some
...trying to something like this...just...it up right and then likewise over here are just
...new it up and I use collection analyzer it looks very similar?
To this code right here
right here so I try and just kind of reuse what I know works.
So, let's try that...
And, that's not very good the reason explodes because of some nuance to the api
immutable array is a value type and the way...into the purpose of...
wrap around existing arrays providing kind of a read-only and immutable interface into a
dot net array so if I just knew it up it's not going to have anything in fact because
a value type it has to have a public parameters constructors generated automatically
for you so it's kind of their as, you know,
...it's something that helps you when you're using instruct in this case because the way the api
...is actually hindrance if you didn't have to...it up or you couldn't do it up you might not run
into this problem likewise down here it's a similar problem whereas going to new
...the that constructor however there's another problem in that even if even if we
could construct suppose there was a constructor the right thing the collection initialize
won't do the right thing to remember how csharp collection analyzers work basically those
break down to calls to an ad method right because this is an immutable array those
ad methods return new immutable arrays so when you get down to the end of it even if this actually
...empty array and called the ad method five times you would
wind up with an empty array right so these are things that are.
Perhaps they are...guidance you would offer that we would like to
...into the compiler maybe but this is kind of chasing after doing this for every
type medina frame...really chasing after
the kind of a long tail of things so by exposing
the analyzer framework in rousing would with something we call code where libraries and go to
...can build a those analyzers and put them in new get packages or
in visual studio in v sixes and make those appear so I just put this up there.
Yesterday upon new get...called core fx analyzers
...install right now it just has to analyzers
okay sorry.
Just to make it very clear when he says we can build he does not
meaning we microsoft means you anyone I mean everybody in this
room myself included I see this project and love...online anybody,
anybody online a future dustin if you're watching this later feel free remember to go
...also contribute this project so what is analyzers do when I add this new get project it adds
core effects analyzers under the analyzers
...the solution explore and under here under this node.
There are two.
Brand-new analyzers there's one to not use immutable
rave t constructor and do not use collection initialized with immutable rarity I brought that
...new get which means actually because these are install...new get the system that collections
...packaged itself could carry along this guidance so that when I get when I install...I guess
...in the editor of I can also include code fixes with it?
Right so the correct correct usage to be to do immutable
...and call empty right that's what you want to start with you
...call the default constructor so we can do that.
...come here fix this one this one I need call create
range to pass in my initialize are and then when I run it works
ok so this is the sort of thing what we envision kind of the world
of libraries and frameworks...where they can carry long guidance to help you use those api
...so in the session after this I'm going to show how to build exactly these things so,
I'm going to step away from this right now and you know,
it's time to talk about language features I think everybody's...is it is all
right so destin showed analyzers and, he actually wrote...
also called csharp essentials which will help people get started using a
new language features and I have that enabled here so we'll run into that a few times before and I'm
in the philosophy for csharp six was very much also this refresh theme if
you will we were so excited to now have a completely fresh compiler code base that we weren't
scared off that we wanted to go and do a lot of those little features that we hadn't really been able to get
...they're too risky or whatever so now we
just we said this is not the time to introduce some
...concept that everybody has to change their
the whole the structure of all their code like casing
this is we don't have any of those line-up we should do little things that will make your code nicer
in little useful ways okay so we tons of those and,
that's what I'm going to just tear through and show you a bunch of just to be clear the air
that everybody wants to the language apart build...up again this time like last time the
time for plus I don't think so they wanted a little features right so that's what I'm...here, yeah,
yes, that's what we've been hearing so we've been going through and finding the little features that make
...sense to us and that a lot of people been asking for so, again,
I have a and...what is very clearly a demo program here is you know,
create some points of appoint class I have
...amount turns them into jason...have to jason to into
...back into an array points and writes...so I'm going to run it just...so,
you know, that it's what it's doing and other than that runtime semantics and really
very interesting in this talk it's all about what the code looks like...start somewhere one of the things that people
are being bugging us with for a long-time and that's been...to us also is this
...the necessity to always have...the to always mention static class
explicitly when you when you access static members the choice have to mention an even
...explicitly when you access its members so on so we said okay now it's time to add a kind-of using
...you can put these guys directly into scope so now you can
say using static which means use the static members of for
instance the system but consul here and you see the
...because I'm not using it but consoles now also great out and,
the id will helpfully tell me that I can simplify accesses of consoled the right
line and just say right line so I like to do that in...document in an apply all
of these...rightly okay I'm...to help a little?
All right so you typically uses for you know,
you often use it for static classes
there always collections of functions that you want to use
...and oftentimes it makes sense to put them into scope like the system and math for instance also I
have an instance of that inside of my point classier which we'll dive into more so,
you see down here master square root again I can go and just get rid of the math.
Get rid of the word math...still there so,
you can use is you can overuse it I think sometimes it'll be really nice to get,
you know, days of the week or whatever em...directly.
Directly in scope...you can also would do it I'm doing some
jason stuff later down here so it might be tempting to go and say newton
...jason doubling that get those j token types just directly and scope here but,
you can also quickly get a bunch of names and scope this j token type called string and now have a conflict here and
string...format so, I'm not going to do that but just to show you that yes,
you can get a lot of abbreviation here you can also get too much if you're not careful
so, looking for the so that was at that the feature there looking further at the
...point here we like everybody else have gotten really,
really fun of immutable types right and...data structures in roslyn
...immutable...just showed immutable and...stuff you however if
you are wanting to build your own immutable types weeping treating you badly in the language
we've been sort of a preferential to people writing mutable types for instance
...properties could only be get set properties so here I would have to
write my properties with explicit backing fields well no more because now we do have
...only or properties you can just...get semicolons you have an
auto property with the backing field that is read-only and the in order to initialize these
you-can assign to them from the constructor directly so I can just
...here and, that assigns to the backing field I can
assign to y here as soon as I go and change that also into an...
Property so now you're not discourage from
using immutable patterns in your code I can just go and remove my backing fields.
And, just use get are only or properties thank you.
And, for my next trick
...one more let's do one more and autumn props as what we said so,
another annoying thing about...properties is that unlike feels you can initialize
indirectly well now you can so you can say equals five-year just like you can infield
...initialized bakke feeling again.
And, that...for that works for the existing...get
...properties as well I'm not going to do that though here because I really like what's coming into my constructor
there.
So, few other things in terms of memory operations that maybe a little
...it it's a little hard to get to the logic from for all
a boiler plate here a good friends in the functional world known as for a long-time like if
...princeton's we...know it from lambdas...result is just
...of all with a single expression and why do you have to have a statement...with
...return statement in it so...today you can choose either to have a statement block or you can
have a just an expression body and now you can do that also for methods and for other function
members sothis is where
...little helper analyzer comes in it's actually suggesting is to me if you notice the curly
...the return a great out here and that is dusters
analyzer telling me that I should consider using an expression body member so I'm...adventures guys I'm
...go do that and what is going to do is to
...focus on screen here but other than that is going to
prude what people would probably have called the land arrow or...I think
...calling the function arrow now but that...put an expression and that is now the body of the
...so we have expression body...
Attitude emphasis mpl stuff like say you have some
operator overload lots of things that are simple methods should be nice to just be able to
inline like that I have all the extra boiler plate forget us
...of...properties and gets a little better have computed...single
...statement even more boiler plate there again we're going to go and just let you use
an expression body member and...takes away everything the curly is again
...and you just really have to put the arrow and the expression that as
a result together and that way again, it gets very concise and this can be over-done.
I would personally recommend against carefully training all
your logic into a single expressions so that you can do this that kind of I know I've
over-done that myself this nomads I should say this is become my favorite feature I didn't know that
would be but rightly become my favorites a bit of a surprise hit as to say but,
it's just like get all that extra stuff out of the way get
...for more logic on your screen really so,
let's keep going on that theme destin is not finished with me here in this and,
this method he's also saying something else he sayings can be simplified
...I have to click their...
When does this can...dustin?
Yes, he says I can converge this call of system...string to what's called...interpolate history
...system stringer format into and interpolate strength so stringer format is
great can do all kinds of stuff for you but it's a little bloated to look at
...in particular what's not nice about it is these place holders you kinda have to keep them in
sync with some argument...lot later and, that can easily create bugs and it's
not easy-to-read so we decided to just built into the language so now I'm going to converges to what we
...strength...this is equivalent to what I had before all right put a little
...in front of you...role here we had to use a dollar sign for something sooner or later so in honor
of visual basic we're going to use dollar to means something with strengths and,
of course is one of the most of the features I've showed you also and bb not the expression by expression body
members by them together on the order properties is of course also and bb
what's happening here really is and you still have your format string here but instead of having...in the
wholes between the curly is you now have expressions...can put any old expression
in here it's a hole in the string you can put real stuff in their compute and,
you can also so if I wanted to put something longer, you know,
system and a ...of we dot something-or-other
dot friday turn that into...whatever you can totally put any kind of expression
in there you can also put the format the alignment specifies informant specify is that you can
insistent string or in...format ok so it's general but,
it's just much nicer to look at I hope you think so too.
You think so too if you do thank...
Someone up there...after here's a here's sort of half of
the heart of my functionality here I'm turning adjacent object j object into
a point okay if it doesn't have the right shape I can't so I'm going to
...argument exception and,
one thing you'll see here is that the destin is telling me I have...the argument name
as a string so he has and...that discovers that he wrote and put into his
...of analyzes here.
...says this is dangers...well if I change the name for instance let's use this
new lovely rename refactoring and I say let's call this...something of course we
will forget to change the name down here and it's going to go out of whack if you use it with notify,
notify probably changed so on that...actually causes errors right
here's just a cosmetic you could say but still you want to get the right name in there so what destin says
...new feature called rename of...your shoulder right here
was bringing your distances do this do this,...
...I have dusting in-box the...is that.
So, let's go do it here consider using name of yes, I will.
I did not do...rename scape of your
...you're out you're right yes I am amazon's on your shoulder telling
disguising thank you I needed the real dustin for that so I wasn't listening to the one
...the box okay here we go and see the using name...
...okay ...name of is really just a
string literal just compiles down to the string that was there before but...checks that the
...likeit.
It's the simplest...assembles feature in the world it's a longer
string literal that will give you errors like how cool is that.
A broad somehow it is cool because now if I
rename it of course it works am with the other guys and.
It'll give you errors if I if I have a typo inherent so on so
it's just again, as a price little thing that just really helps you of course it doesn't have to be
an argument name I could go and make this I'm referring to the classed name here we could make this
...straying we could put a
hole in here and we could take the name of point and that way.
We make sure that if we change the name of the class.
...here then we go we would actually go and, fix it up everywhere as well so
am those two features work nicely together I also want call attention
to this block of condition here this is where.
I check that my jason is in the right shape to form
a point out of ok so first I have to check that the argument itself is not...if it isn'tindexing
two-x and see if there is one or whether that's null and if it is and then I'll make
sure that its type is indeed an integer and this is where usage a token type...injure and do the same and for
y so that's a lot of logic and most of it is about checking for...and isn't that just annoying yes,
that is very annoying thank you so,
what we decided is to smooth that over...if you common cases so,
instead of checking here that this is null I can use the
null conditional dot or the question dot or also that was not
a question also sometimes affectionately known as the
...operator because it's got to...and by...swirled hair that...
Not particularly ldc by everybody knows elvis...cool to have something named after
So, what that means is that we're going to see if the thing on the left-hand side here is
null and if it is...we're not going to do the
dot then the whole expression here is just going to be null which is not
...token type that integers so it's going to fails appropriate if it isn't null then we're going to
dot and get the value out so she's been inline all check drill all right?
We can kill headlining code and with another question we can kill another line
of code and it's like a real bloodbath here.
We can also do a for indexing so,
I don't even have to check of their that...self is...I can say question and front
here as well and that means if it isn't null then do the indexing otherwise the whole thing becomes
null right so I really just again I
boiled down to let's get rid of all...play let's just
have the core intent here which is...the...hasn't got
...that are integers then throw the exception okay there's just the core like...
Glad you like it so,
let's see we can have time for another one...
We can colder here for so, let's look at the method that takes so that was sort of the big
ones let's look at a few smaller ones...to someone you may also be significant this is the method takes you
from the point back to jason okay so the inverse of what we just saw if
jason had...members called x and y we were to...object initialized here which we've had
...three we've just said something like x e x equals
capital x or something like that comment...same for why it would
all-in-one expression declare...initialized because they were the initialize through
...index or that hasn't been possible before but, it is now as you
were probably already guessing here is I was leading up to it so you can now
...initialize to an index as well if you can actually hit the right keys so,
you can do this and, why is?
Why and now the
j object is initialized in one fell swoop
in the expression here so just alongside your you remember initialize as an uptick...you can now
also initialized elements which of course means I can go and controlled
...dot here inline temper variable that's nice
...great well that is dustin again telling me while this could be
an expression body member and of course now it all became very smoothly?
Dustin they've...
We can talk about a few more things quickly around exceptions.
So, this is a method I'm not actually using it here
in the main program but let's look at anyway there's a method that.
Has the try catching it and it's and asic
...ok try catch finally here and we have to admit that there was a hole
in the in our implementation of await that it couldnt...can be used in catching
find blocks before because we thought my god we don't know-how that...even work we're I guess we weren't
a smart back-to-the-future for future yourselves were smarter yet we turned out to becomes
...with time so after we shipped...we're like we can figure this out like
it people run into the need to I want to
log something asynchronous lay down here in my catch blog I want to say there was an exception login
somewhere but if I try if I say repository?
Data log.
...log method...well that sucks because I want to actually not and exit the catch
...before I'm done so, how do I do that people have terrible work-arounds for...like we should do the
channel work around...the compiler rather than everybody doing it every time right that's what we...for let's that's actually
...our...keep your so now you can indeed await inside of a
catch blog and it just works it just doesn't?
It doesn't...before it's done and even better in the finally
blog my god is that difficult to work around repository...let's say I want to close
...thing here after I can now weight doing that asynchronous and you don't come out of the
finally block until you're actually done which is what finally blog supposed to be
...so very nice one little extra feature which is already
and vb we added to csharp as well as actually also
...you the ability to filter exceptions which is a tiny little feature
but it's actually kinda nice sometimes so I can...condition I catch block and say
...one do this when say some and bogus thing
here either occurrences is greater than three otherwise don't catch it don't even
touch it ok and it's sort of like putting and if blog inside the catch
...and re throwing but is different because
the exception doesn't get modified it doesn't get its is origin point of
origin over written right so you can so it just keeps flying and it doesn't
with the final receiver of the exception can see where did this really originate rather than having been
...return is also popular for dirty tricks
like having, having exception filters that always a
falls like dynamic actually exception but they log something along the way or tricks like that
...only catch it on tuesdays...
yes but that's not a dirty trick that's legit so, that's it those are the
...features of csharp six there a few tiny ones that we may not ...
you may not discover but these are the so the big ones so I hope you like it?
We can debug this stuff as well right we can about this stuff...my machine to do a little bit of look at a few
the debugging features.
But, it's kind of a...story I'm going to continue
this code because the story of debugging of csharp code at least
...came to language features is a sad one
...appear remembers that visual studio twenty-five.
We brought back at it and continue right we did a bunch of work it for
...for visual basic had been taken away from visual basic
...brought back and twenty fiveand, we...to csharp.
And, then we continue to evolve the language and failed to convert to
...and continue such that every time you try to use a new a new language feature
you would stub your toe and say sorry you can't actually edit this
...debug time to the point that now it's almost impossible to find places in twenty
thirteen you can really actually meaningful use...continue
...thread application so we decided that with rebuilding kind of
the entire stack here that we wanted to address that and make it so that no,
...features left behind and you can do these sorts of things so I'm going
...break point and I'm going to try to semitic continue so let's see here what should
I do when I'm going to create a list and somebody's things are things you can do
today okay and create list I could I could create
...sort of thing pretty easily today what I couldn't do before.
Is press control dot here a debug time?
And, generate that class okay.
That works down here there is no purpose google.
Okay, it doesn't work.
Now I want to populate that I've got the person class so that's good so let's go ahead and
it's through a person in here.
Sets...properties that don't exist yet like the start exploring at debug time and change my
...same ads will do like ical or.
Well, they're, they're lovely should...thank you okay it's just like just for the people in the back
...it right...semicolons down here again
...press control dot to bring up to generate the property for my
Going-to go ahead and actually I can hover over this as well I think there we go we're going to generate a new type...gives me a lot
of options because doesn't...I want to do with this yet so I'm going to generate a new type and we're coming here we're going to make this
...untied whoops there we go.
And, that...ad down here as well.
They can adder in a member to that so as you can see...got a previous can add brown into the...
And, we'll generator I color property and right now if I look at the
airlift there are no errors there are no squiggles there's no purpose wiggles I'm still debugging this program I
started debris point I swear.
I know you don't believe me right because this is never worked.
So, I'm going to another will have myself in here.
You can see intelligence picking everything up because they're actually...in the file.
I can't tell you my own...this morning that blue odious minor blue.
So, we'll go ahead and generate that in a member right and I can step over this.
...me hold sure I've got in my list I've got
two-person instances a person...properties set everything's there.
...first staggering things you can do it in continue time now for example,
if I just wanted to get the...know let's get...people with blue eyes so
...just, you know.
Blue eyes I could do things like this.
I believe I can do things like this.
Just...get myself.
And, my name ago and that if I come back up here I can move instruction pointer.
Control shift...ten by the way moves
...pointer has for years...shortcut to know step over that and sure
enough I've done a link expression and editing continue time which...you know,
the machinery underneath, you know, like expressions it's done crazy things under the hood in order to
...a...that ...all of...business and captures and everything so this
is very cool now as I said no language feature left behind
right and, in continues great sometimes I don't want...geo very often that's not what I'm doing very often I just
want to introspective little bit further into the stuff that I the types of
in values that...already have my program and often it's very hard, for example,
if I want to define the person with blue
eyes from a watch that would be difficult there's no longer difficult
reason if goes because I couldn't has a lambda...here and I have to have one right.
Sure, enough where it is or I...come over to the media window do the same thing.
However, type things right...the on.
...intelligence doesn't help me.
...so really taking the time to rethink the debugging space to make sure that the
breadth of the languages available here so all the things that...showed you that are really work
in expressions like question dot of those things...debugging windows now and in
the rc this is the visual studio rc so this is working today we have more to do here and we're
continuing to try it out and try and get as much as we can packed in...gm's a
...out give feedback we'd love to hear, you know, so, that we can smooth of the edges and make sure we have
everything that's possible to get working actually working varied.
Now before we go on to some future
e things we're going to computer things I want to mention...the csharp essentials
project tool I just want to mention very quickly if you're interested in trying
that out you can get that from extensions and updates in visual studio you can go to the
online tab and you can do a search for csharp essentials.
And, it will show up right here ok and I'll give
you some analyzers and refactoring and fixes for taking code and seeing
where csharp six feature could remove some boiler plate and make your program
more concise user read that sort of thing
...ok now last but not least we want to look at a few things
...into the future so, I'm going to bring up something that we haven't brought up in a
while it's been it's been a few years.
So, I'm going to go to other windows.
Number of the csharp interactive window, yeah.
We haven't seen...in a long-time in fact we haven't
seen so long that many of you may bit have not seen it at all but,
the future of interactive window is kind of...a scratch pad or a place where I can
go and explore csharp code I can I can play around and explore api
...a and what really is though to me is the world's most
inefficient overly glorified calculator
...coming here and type expressions that would be csharp and the amount of effort and compute our to
do that was just insane we wasted cycles like you wouldn't believe to embed two-plus
two but I can do I can do other things I do interesting things as well I'm going to go
and ...a couple references we add the pound
aredirective here to add references into the system at a couple references
...aren't there by default and, let's go ahead and add a
few namespaces so-and-so using diagnosis and diagnostics and system that
a link now this is not in the rc
okay this is something that we've we stop working on for a while we had we had really
forge pretty far ahead with it and we stop working on for...and this is something that we have a
roadmap to go and invest in very soon so following
are tm we have roadmap are get a project that you can go check out we posted the
design nodes from the interactive group that's working in this window and working on the entire
rebel and scripting story on get...definitely check that out if you're interested but
it's this really cool thing and it relates debugging because part of the roadmap is...
we want this to be part of the debugging experience today it's kind of a separate thing we get kind of a separate little,
little universe we can play with some csharp code construct some objects and play with them
would be great if I could take that and then apply it and use it right on my application running
application doesn't you said a strange...a...something...like what
...the redevelopment loop that's a that's balding building, you know,
marching boldly into a like nineteen fifty eight right putting a redevelopment loop into
csharp so case people don't have that yes abbreviation in their vocabulary anymore,
yeah, so, I'm going-to go ahead and I'm going to types
and code like the sorts of things you could do in here let's say we want to find?
The memory pigs on this machine
right find the processes maybe that are running with more memory so I'm going to use a link here.
And,...cool about the rebels that it's not sure essential your parents
...your grand...is a full intelligence full...a shun quick-fix is all work in here
...things will gray out all of...the same experience you get in the editor will work in the
...inside the revel so get all processes here say where the.
P dot working said sixty-four is greater than all
...to megabyte we go.
And, then I will select anonymous type.
...process name.
And, the working set.
Looks like a tighter right so now that's what I've got a memory...eigen for each through that I can
...the top-level here...we'll say for each pig.
And, memory pigs I'm...things like,
you know,...complete for braces curly braces and all that sort of sort of features
you expect intelligence will do actually I forgot to use system?
Using system that rewrite line will pass and pig we go.
And, see what the processes are that are killing me on my machine there's devon.
...I don't know why link needs that much memory but anyways so,
that's just a quick look this is still here this is still something we're working on it is upon get other sources are
there you can build them yourselves...the product it's not that hard to do I've I
did just yesterday to put in here so that's just a brief look at that you had some stuff you and assures
well right yeah, that we should...
Obviously when this gets online is also great way of
exploring language features because again like in
...they're going to actually work everywhere, yeah, that's kind of a new-style.
Actually make things work.
I...so, let me go and switch over to and I've got all
the gis gretchen you've got me...this is crohn's what idi...always
...for you have works little bettering from.
So, that's sort of the near future light and soon after rt
embellish is where we targeting the...starting to come online and start getting better from then.
In sort of further future we realized back in back around
the january that if we if we want to start thinking about
a next version of csharp after csharp six now so good time to start thinking
while most of the team are still working on
...fifteen wave stuff announces the time to
...thinking and as we went opensource with our with our code bases and,
took all those implementation level discussions
opensource we've also gone open-source without language design process
ok so we still sit around and rooms and have language
sign meetings but then I go type...notes from that and I put them out on copeland on again, no,
...to...code place if you want to see the design
...procedure six complexes where you go and put them out and get...and,
people put so, get up we're here and get up?
If we look at ...this one here I filtered for design nodes these
are nodes from the language design meetings since january just all-out there with all
our discussion about what should possibly be
and csharp seven what are the kind of themes we might want to focus on what could the shapes
ba features and it's all very nebulous right now it's in the
cloud but also in other ways nebulous a like what will the final
themes be but some things are starting to crystallize and might be one of those situations where future
meds looks back and said that you thought you were going to do that
position seven hot but, we started the process so I really encourage you to go out and get
have actually the start putting...your own
language proposals we have let's have a look here we have currently hundred
thirty-six open language proposals just since january and get that we will look at in
time...discussion about of course people discuss like crazy the.
The designs that we put
up and we get tons of good feedback so we kind of in this loop with everyone all the
way rather than sort of put something out after a year or two years and seeing if
it sticks as really helping us I think home
...on the right things so we're pretty.
Right now we have a pretty ambitious kind of plan for csharp seven we want to do
many things and we want to do big things this may peter out may not that's our we started going
boldly...one of the things that we want to do and one...started so early is that we
...try to attacked some of the big problems that we've attacked before
and failed okay or that have really become big problems over the last couple years
...world involving is now no longer esoteric just saying about
null ability tracking and
...in your language is no longer esoteric to have
tools and mainstream language a lot of things that have been...great languages like
...and other functional languages for a while but never really made it
into the mainstream we can now they're starting to move into the mainstream and people are starting to be
ready for them so now it's time for us to think about it again so what I have here for instance is the sort of
a work list of the features that we have ever looked at in this round of design and
kind of targeted into which ones are we interested in research and...in
...ability like tracking whether a field is intended to be sometimes
null or intended not to be and then checking your code to see if you're adhering to that tony
...called the null pointer his billion-dollar mistakes we'll try to get you back about half of
...billion ok so that's sort of the ambition and,
all of this tracks proposals and here...as another one that...interested in and I think
the main scenario for that is that in language like csharp
...asymmetry when you look at function...so this is a proposal that's
...get-up-and-go look this...asymmetry between input and output to
a function you can take several things saying...you can only one thing out and we kind of
want to restore that feeling of symmetry that you can also have multiple results
so the approach we're taking to...is that it looks something like this here's a to
...type...return position it has the
components consisting of type and name just like parameter lists so we kinda using parameter list
...analogy there is something we want to do we want to enable you to write
table literals so you can return when you have this return type here you can return it's
...values here and they get type by that by that
...here you can deconstruct...so,
at the receiving side recall tally I get this table back I can immediately deconstruct into
...component values so on and then we put that up there we discuss what are the person contact
...and people just swarm here with commentary and,
it's good it's really good feedback...people who have experience
...and deep thoughts so on and that helps
...gaidar design process so let's go back to the work list here and just quickly
look at some of the things that aren't top here I talked about triples I talked about
nobility another thing we're talking about is pattern matching and,
we're talking about sort of recurs or algebraic data types those
to kind of go together a little bit one of the things that we find is that
in traditional object-oriented programming that csharp was kind of
...for you put a lot of you functionality on the inside of the objects the object,
... classes have hierarchies and height
in hierarchies you override virtual methods and the objects...what they can
do that's a great paradigm for a lot of things one thing it's not-so-good for is if?
If your object represent data that exists in multiple
...sent over the wire and is used differently in different places
like I might use the data differently on a service in the cloud and I use it on the device
...pulls down the data so on so having...functionality wrapped up with the data doesn't make sense at this point you want to
have functionality on the outside functional languages a good for that and the way
they then distinguish so we're boring from those look at of sharp and other functional languages
for inspiration and what-you
want-to do there is to write a function that is able to essentially switch over the shape of the object
says one of these into that is one of these and do that and pattern matching
...mechanism for doing that succinctly and beautifully so we're taking these things
...inspiration from say of
...trying to figure out how can they look good?
In a csharp context how can we make them feel native to csharp it's not
like some transplant from another world and, that's a process that we're going through right now
encourage you to go here look if feedback help us get the rightplan for
csharp seven even though it may be years before it's actually reality even though it might not be coliseum
seven who knows so,
please do that that's as far as we are with that so now is where we're going to switch back to
...for second-tier?
You can I can just click here so why I say a few things
we're going to have a little bit of qa we would like you to come to the microphones if you have a
question you can start going up there and we'll have time for...questions maybe and,
then after the session...hang around here and answer a few more questions though
they're probably throw me out to get ready for the next recording...next streaming dustin
...run-off to another room where he will give his next talk about writing
...so if you're interested in going to that and you don't know where it is you can follow dusting
...he runs out the door when I'm done and answering questions here are also go to the
booths and hang out there so common,
common answer all those questions...we didn't have time for...session all right
and before I take the we take the questions again I want to remind you
if you didn't already if you were grumpy and dusting convinced due to weight
please evaluate the session now hope you're happy now and we really hope you're happy all right?
So, we have a question here in the middle...question about dot net cool versus
...framework...the language how the language relates to that so, for example,
could we see teachers in the language spec for csharp that
...apply to cool been future?
Could we say features that only...core in the future I
think in principle yes I think if core
takes over ninety some percent then we aim then or, you know,
...sufficiently big section of the world or of the address
simple space for new version of csharp or visual basic then we would certainly consider it
there are things we can do with also with the core clr that we might not be able to do on
the desktop in the future so it would be a consideration it's not in the plan right now to differentiate
...it's better if we can keep it all-in-one dialect but it's certainly possible?
Another question and the middle here,
yeah, my question is you...a syntax where you don't have to have a temporary
...return you can make things very concise now with refactoring is their way to
celebrate points that you can still see the value before it gets returned.
Yes, I believe you can celebrate point on the expression...but,
to actually see the valuable...return so,
after the expression has been...no I don't play not within the expression body no
unfortunately...that would be very nice...polling and
...have...everything about it at the great-great suggestion.
Any more questions where one over there yes in...to pool list of
features the plans for rename to whose name tools yes and that is what I
...depends on what you mean by named these tools work
...the tools themselves do not have
...type does not have...the members do have names in the proposal we have now is that
...yes we think that when you get a when you get a tool back from a
methods say it's really.
Kind of confusing if you get three
...three strings like which is which how do I how do I decide what to do with them then I have to go
and read documentation it's better if itself documenting so we want some form of names in
there now what's not clear is should troubles be equivalent across different
names for the same members if they have the same types or stuff like that that's in
...design details by the current plan is definitely to go with names so again in
parallel with parameter list you would sort of have
return lists when they're in that position with names and types thank you
...we can have one quick question let's take...here.
So, I was just wondering if there's ...thoughts to like a opie and doing stuff
like exception handling more natively was attributes so,
aspect oriented programming is what you mean by a
...right yes a few people...something else that's typically what it means.
We haven't yet found the appetite or the motivating scenarios
for adding it to the core of the language obviously the more we
am a open up the compiler logic through api
nb...I think we're gradually introducing more opportunities for
doing some for other people or for outside of the language doing something
based on attributes and rewrites or something like that it's not been of course scenario we've
designed for but it's something that
...drive future evolutions of the rustling api and
...of time thank you very much.